welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
so as i mentioned in um the email when i
reached out to you
is that uh i organized a stoic group
here in in toronto and then we can't
meet in person so i launched this kind
of online
stoic uh presence called the stoa
and one theme that is popping up right
now is death
and so i thought of you obviously
a fellow canadian and former torontonian
um so i guess maybe i'll just start with
this uh
this quote that from plato that's coming
from mind and then i'll just
see how it lands for you um i'm afraid
that
other people do not realize that the one
aim of those who practice philosophy
in the proper manner is to practice for
death and dying
well i don't know if it's the only one
but without it
you can't you can't really achieve very
much i would say
you know use the word gravitas a minute
ago
it's where we get our adjective grave of
course and
we misapprehend grave it means profound
it doesn't mean quote serious or it
doesn't mean
you know the absence of humor or a deep
regard for beauty or
it simply means your capacity to be
grateful for being alive
is rooted in the deep abiding
and ongoing understanding that soon
enough you won't be
and if you can't pull that off you know
those
it's not a tightrope act it's a it's a
mingling
if you can't pull that off you're just
not a grown-up
that's it i mean it doesn't sound very
tolerant
it isn't very tolerant you know
tolerance is for people who got a lot of
room
but in a time like this the notion that
um
that you get to have your you know your
own take on what it means
to possibly possibly die
no it's not possible it's one of the few
givens of your life i can tell you this
i i used to be the death guy although
your association with me and my face is
still
that but i've i i seem to have moved on
to certain
in some people's mind but but uh
when i was i saw pretty routinely
the idea that people proceeded as if
they knew they were going to die
if you were to ask them of course and
you raised the contemplation to
to the level of something deliberate
okay a very handy example so i'm in a
room full of people i don't know
and apropos apparently have nothing i
ask them how many people in this room
know they're going to die
well you know the predisposition of my
audience and so on would be that
virtually every hand would go up
and here's the thing
i would have to say how do you know that
you know that
this second order awareness right a much
subtler thing
if i asked you if you're alert to this
piece of information
you'd say yes but if i ask you what does
it do to your days
ah this is a much different question and
the chances are very good
that it does virtually nothing to most
people who have their hand up
so a good parallel to that would be
i mean you're too young to remember this
but it wasn't that long ago
people were lining up at the gas pumps
particularly in the united states and
fist fighting for position
in the lineup because there was an oil
shortage it was very temporary
right and it was an aberration
if you had to ask people in those days
is there enough oil in the ground
for everybody yes or no they would have
said yes
and how could you tell they believed
there was enough oil and the answer is
by how they lived
and how they purchased right and how
they oriented themselves and decisions
they made every morning and
how far away from work they lived
i mean it went on and on and on that's
how you could tell that people knew
there was enough oil now the truth is
there wasn't enough oil there was never
enough oil but i didn't say if it was
true
i said the people know it people know
there was enough and the answer is yes
so if you take out the word oil and you
put in the word dying
into the exact same scenario
how can you tell that people know that
they're dying and the answer is
you can't and i'm talking about
sort of dominant culture in north
america and the reason you can't
is because the word no
means something it doesn't mean
awareness
it means there's a there's a level
at which your life is ongoingly informed
by this thing that you know
you know how to breathe and you do so at
least most of us most of us know how to
walk around and we do so
most of us know where we're supposed to
go to work at least until recently
and we do so that's how you can tell
that the knowledge is there
but the knowledge of dying leaves no
trace
in north america because it's not
knowledge it's suspicion
it's fear it's um it's
idle curiosity but as a piece of
known sort of existential
information it's not a known thing
and this is why i last why i had a job
that was my job security
is it was predicated on the
understanding that nobody knew that they
were going to die
virtually nobody knew and i can
i can show you to the cows come home
examples of
people who uh who came to their dying
either shocked or feeling abused
or feeling you know uh sort of
mishandled or mistreated by life
because the inevitable and the given
finally
came to call well if you knew you were
going to die
where does the sense of grievance about
dying come from
and more often than not people look
shocked you know
and finally take this notion about
sudden death which is
often the objection that was raised to
my stuff
was yeah but this is all very useful if
you see your death coming from a long
way off which is hilarious because the
people who did
see their death coming from a long way
off didn't thank me i can tell you that
but the people who who imagined that
somehow sudden death is a completely
different animal
obviously i've never died and secondly
misapprehend this thing
if we know that we're going to die
there's nothing sudden about dying
is there because the word sudden means
i didn't know
not that you didn't know it was today
but you didn't know at all
sudden death is a confession that's
about truancy
that's what you're saying when you talk
about sudden death
as a shock as something somehow is
beneath your dignity or has no mercy in
it
in actual fact there's no such thing as
sudden death
not no such thing whatsoever that's a
dereliction of duty
to imagine that there's a thing called
sudden death your death is a given
and it's an ongoing reality
and the amazing thing about these days
that we're in right now
is when we watch older people and old
folks home die in their dozens
suddenly suddenly
we imagine that this is a visitation
from some darker place
and where does the notion of
dark death come from from the sense
that we don't get a vote i mean most
north americans are addicted
so so terminally
to self-direction that anything like
what we're going through now
the idea that you have to stay at home
as a kind of
punishment or as a kind of arbitrary
whimsical invasion into the natural
order of things it's just
it really speaks to how thin our
understanding of our daily life actually
was
and our capacity to live it in any deep
sort of way
very very compromised and and that
that's really what today
these days are for is glimpsing
ourselves
in the act of being shocked by things
that were
though unprecedented completely
predictable
what's coming up is um
you know you know that quote i read in
the beginning and then a lot of these
exercises that stoics and whatever do
it could be these cute cognitive
intellectual exercises like okay
you know you you'll you know you'll die
right whatever and everyone puts their
hand up
but then um there's a difference between
kind of
knowing in an intellectual sense and
actually feeling it and having like an
emotional relationship or emotional
knowingness
um and i wonder how you cultivate that
like you personally how you cultivate
that and how do other people cultivate
that
well first of all not many people seem
to cultivate it so you're already
talking about a rare thing
but this is this is why it's so you know
i say that out loud in response to what
you said
and i'm sure people listening say dude
that's way overstated
well first of all you didn't follow me
around from day to day when i worked in
the death trade
it's not overstated i have no reason to
exaggerate this dilemma
right i'm not getting paid more for
anything i do
by virtue of lamenting on this level
about this kind of thing
so that's the first thing it's extremely
rare
to find people who are informed by their
dying
you see so let's use the example of the
small b
buddhist who when when
encouraged to contemplate these things
will come up with this nugget
which they deem to be helpful to the
rest of us
oh everybody's dying all the time
see as soon as i say that there's a kind
of involuntary new age
peace to all all of us that just start
doing this
yes yes we're all dying all that that
sounds right
in a bizarre way it feels right and so
it must be right
and so we're just dying all the time so
so this is great news because if we're
dying all the time there's nothing to do
because it's just happening all the time
not to each not to various people in the
population no to
everyone in some kind of regular
uh patterned fashion
really so if that's true then there's no
such thing
really as the terminal diagnosis it
doesn't change anything at all
it's just another day at the office
really
so so you don't believe anything changes
as a consequence of becoming symptomatic
okay so you know what i'm telling you
from this first of all
there is a reality called dying and it's
a different reality
from when you're not dying and though i
don't know anything about your
you know your personal health
circumstances i'll bet anything you're
not dying
i'm not dying at the moment
but i know the difference i know when i
am beginning to die
i know the changes that will come see
and it's an
insult to dying people to imagine we're
all dying all the time
but dying is a is a
it's a kind of skill you see it's a it's
not a skill that virtually anybody seeks
out i don't think
but the skillfulness is not a coping
strategy the skillfulness
is an ability you have an ability
granted to you with years-long practice
that you might be able to die as i call
it
wise that's to say that
it's your manner of dying that becomes
the thing the way by which you sum up
your take on life
that's what dying is it's your chance to
to be somewhat authoritative
given what you were led into during the
course of your life
maybe authoritative is not the right
word just skillful
and and your obligation when you're
dying comes
is to embody that kind of skillfulness
for the fearful and the distraught
that surround you not to reassure them
everything's going to be okay
whatever the hell that's supposed to
mean but rather that you assure them
that this dying is not an intrusion
into the natural order of things no
matter what form it takes
whether it's a virus you know or a
cancer
or a car wreck or a slipping on the ice
whatever form it takes it's not a
rupture
you see it's a rupture into our
artificial sense of continuity
yes but but as a contemplated thing
it's an assurance it's a way by which
you can you can take to your
days as a duck takes to water
you're not always deep underneath it but
it's forever
around you and to a great extent
underneath you and buoying you up and
reminding you fairly constantly and
fairly faithfully
that it's not far from you
this is what the greeks meant by the
word daemon
which we get demon right okay so we we
have a kind of
generic kind of fairy tale-ish kind of
idea
which we might call uh
um oh man i just blanked on the thing
not fairy godmother but a guardian angel
like this kind of idea
and you can tell by the characterization
that
that it's very benign and it's to that
extent it's very welcome
but angel the the greek word angel
simply meant
messenger it had nothing to do with
benign had nothing to do with beneficent
or none of that
it simply meant a bringer of news
and the word daemon from which we get
blumen
was virtually the same thing the the
daemon
was something that was born when you
were born
uh that has um typically followed you
around town
that has more or less faithfully
answered the bell answered the call
every time you didn't and the one who
will be there
sitting at the end of your bed on your
dying day
and leaning in very gently and asking
inquiring whether or not you have any
questions
that's that's the one who was born when
you were born who seems to know you
a little better than you've ever been
inclined
so and if you think of the contemporary
meaning of the words now or the
associations with them
angel and demon we're at pains to keep
them apart
in hopes that an angel means is nothing
but good
and can offset the presence of something
quote demonic
right you know but all this
misapprehends the the language
and misapprehends the old understanding
so
so that's what you're dying is among
other things is your
demon not your personal name
but the one who's who will not let you
down
who will not mistake you for somebody
else
or have too much to drink and follow
somebody else home hmm
yeah this is um yeah it's kind of
strange because we just met like like
like like one minute we pressed records
the first time i met you
and anyone who knows me i talk about the
damon all the time i was
actually writing about it in the journal
um you know socrates he
used used his daemon as a kiting spirit
and that i like the idea like eudemonia
right it's a good relationship with your
daemon
um and ever since this this covet thing
happened
it's like it's so complex this is
chaotic i can't i couldn't think right i
didn't know what to do
i just basically handed the keys over to
damon and i just feel quite alive and
just energetic about this right now
and i like this idea of building a
relationship with your demon
and just kind of emancipating at other
people's demons
so they can build a relationship with it
as well i don't know if that's
the correct phrasing of it but yeah i'm
curious what you think about that how to
build a really really good relationship
with your demon well i'm not sure
that the best expression is to call it
your
demon the reason i'm hesitant is because
the language of personal possession in
anglo-north america
indicates some kind of dominion it just
involuntarily does you know
you say my cat we know what you mean
if you say my clothes we know what you
mean if you say my dem
my dame on it's pretty similar no
right and the truth is it's not your
demon to
to order around the place or to get in
order or to
um to milk for all it's worth or any of
those kinds of things
this is a it's a kind of you could call
it a
house deity you could call it a domestic
deity in the old days
when there were no central houses of
worship
it's quite clear in the eastern
mediterranean that every house had an
altar
and that the head of the household was
basically the the priest
of the household and it was responsible
for
administrations and so on you could
imagine
damon as a kind of residual memory a
kind of vestigial memory of a time
when every house was responsible for
maintaining
its deities and the ancestors were
buried under the floor
i mean just to give the fullness to the
circumstance right
and so with that in mind how to
cultivate it well
i mean the first order business i think
is the same way
we would do if we weren't able to share
english readily
and we were intending to do something
deep and abiding and maybe useful to
other people
and i had enough time to prepare and you
spoke french
then my responsibility to some extent
would be to learn enough french to get
by
see that's cultivating a relationship
you learn the language
of what you claim to hold in high regard
so then is it possible that the daemon
has a language
of course it is maybe not a language in
quite the way you and i are using
english at the moment
but this is a hint um
i came to dying very in a very similar
way i came to realize that dying was a
god
the death was a god and then when death
comes in the room you know it doesn't
it doesn't mean you harm but it
certainly means you
and so if you have a god suddenly in
your house
i mean the first order of business is do
you exercise the kind of
radical hospitality right the greeks
were
all about hospitality i mean in the uh
they have remarkable range of vocabulary
to denote different kinds of hospitality
and there was one you exercise for
people that you knew that you were bound
to by blood
that kind of kinship and there's a
different kind of hospitality that you
exercised
when you didn't know the person and they
didn't know you and there's another kind
that ends the formalities of the
hospitality so that it's not
forever lingering and we're not able to
proceed to the next part of our day or
or our life
they really had this highly highly
sorted out
you take this that kind of sophisticated
understanding
and approach this this house deity
is the daemon who knows your name
and who excuse the experience about who
knows your shit too
if if that's if that's the case then the
first
hospitable thing is the same thing you
would do for me probably if i was at
your house which is
um you've probably been traveling a long
way can i get you something to drink
and you would offer a range of
possibilities
[Music]
that's how you do it you inquire after
its well-being
you don't imagine that it's
self-sufficient the way a monotheistic
understanding of anything beautified
tends to
make that terrible mistake of imagining
because it's deified it has
no need of us we're the only needy
things in the
in the natural order and the gods or in
this case
the god has no need of us whatsoever
simply demands
but this is a kind of broken down
understanding
of the old hospitality of having a god
in your house
now nobody gets a chance to have god in
their house because we're obliged to be
in god's house instead
he said it's a gross misapprehension of
of the responsibility that we have
i think um
because i i i like that a lot and i'm
wondering how biased i am by using the
term your daemon
because like locally like
propositionally like i i understand that
like it's just your local access to the
daemon
and then that uh that girl who did that
book
eat pray love she did this interesting
ted talk
where she was saying how artists in the
past they didn't view their creativity
was their own it was just from the
daymond and now the modern artists
they're all struggled and tortured and
all that stuff because they view it you
know it's
their ego if they're not producing then
something's wrong with them
and i notice when i get kidnapped by ego
or i feel that kind of ego a tendency
that daemon just dries up
like i i lose access to it i lose that
relationship
and i'm i'm at the edge of my thinking
so i'm
curious if the ego how how that's
related to death
or my relationship or lack of
relationship with death
well egos are kind of technical words
we're just speaking about things greek a
few minutes ago
and technically the ego
is a very austere
individual um
i would say thread bear frankly i would
say
kind of bereft of association that's the
dilemma with the contemporary
understanding of ego
you know ego me i
am it's about as remote
and sort of um siberian as you can get
you know kind of northern boreal lost on
the in the tundra
or a drift on an iceberg that's a go amy
to me
so i come to it this way
i saw a lot of people to death's door
lots of them hundreds and hundreds uh
this can really inform you
if you're lucky it can traumatize you
if you don't have much good fortune and
you're not working pretty hard
one of the things i saw routinely
was people thrashing about for something
that they more or less called
meaning the idea that
they had to find it like it was this
kind of scavenger hunt
in actual fact meaning is made
it's not found it's made and by made i
don't mean
arbitrarily i mean through enormous
layers and levels of of
arduous focus and devotion and so on
meaning is made
here's a good example we have
the english word true or truth
right now it's not an english word in
fact
the word itself is english but our
understanding of it is not
so just bear with me for a minute a
little bit of a etymological history
lesson here
so the word toyan is an old english word
but it never meant what we use it to
mean today
there's the irony the vocabulary is old
english
but the syntactical
meaning of the word is latin it's roman
okay now the roman word is veritas as
you probably know
i went to a school that has that as its
um
what logo i guess you would call it it's
hilarious
and we take it to mean you know going
all the way back to the people that i
think you're enamored of
and uh beyond we take it to mean
some kind of enduring unchanging
indwelling formless uh
you can count on it pretty solid that
kind of thing
you know and it's in its uh in juris
prudence it's a very important concept
you know the truth the truth will set
you free you know
and so on well the word
true signified the following
for people who use the word the
ancestors of this language i'm speaking
to you in
meant this by it true was a verb
it wasn't an adjective and it was never
a noun
it was something you did it wasn't
something you had or you owned or you
saw
or you held or you gave from one person
to the other
it was a verb it was an activity
it was a kind of collective discernment
and and the form that it took is people
with real standing in the village or the
community or the clan or
the tribe tended to be older people of
course
they had a name that's where the old
understanding comes from their name
wasn't even theirs it was given to them
as an acknowledgement of the work
they've done the service the
achievements and so on
and their name would change periodically
through their lives
properly so as you do already you're
beginning to get the idea
that your standing in the community
changes and it changes your name
accordingly
so somehow what your life
begins to mean is being attested
and attributed by others not by you
there's no such thing as self made
in other words we have this word
automaton
right i said two greek words which
together
literally means to be mothered
by yourself which would from a
from a genetic point of view and other
points of view
probably be the principal
obscenity that you could imagine to be
self-mothered
to push your mother and all that
mothering out of the way
and you're going to assume the ability
to take this
upon yourself so these people would
attest
to a given something they would
they would bear witness to a given
something particularly in times of
trouble
like the time we're in and these old
people's willingness to put their status
in the community
on the line by declaring themselves in
favor of
a particular kind of action or a view or
something like that
was assigned to the rest of the people
because these people were truly you see
that's what they were doing
and the only vestige of this that
survives us today
is of all places is in carpentry
there are things in carpentry called
truing sticks most people don't use them
anymore
but it worked like this if you had a
long piece of wood and you're trying to
make a level plane
you wouldn't just trust your eye running
down 8 or 12 or 15 feet of wood
to work out the various what you would
do is you take two sticks
that were exactly the same proportion
and you'd lay one let's say 10 feet away
from you and one
three feet away from you at this point
you're not looking at the base wood
anymore
you're looking at the top lines or
planes
of these two small pieces of wood and
you're checking their alignment
these two sticks are telling you about
the movement of the wood across
time see and across space these are
called truing sticks
and that's who elders are in a living
community
they're truing the subterranean
you know uh architecture and their
willingness to
to testify accordingly and to put their
the meaning of their lives on the line
and their status on the line
probably attests to how quote
true what they're saying is and that's
the currency that people went with
so all of that is simply me suggesting
to you
that the meaning of your life is not
something that you
cobble together the meaning of your life
is attributed to you by others you see
and and in dying more than any other
time of life it becomes very apparent
that you are not you're not exercising
authority
of course the root word of authority is
the one who writes it down
right so that's not what you're getting
to do what you're doing
is you're entrusting the meaning of your
life to others
as you have done involuntarily during
the course of your life
now you basically have no other choice
and now you realize
what a um awake is
awake is the time at which for the first
time
at the cessation of your life your
life's meaning
begins to gather momentum and gravitas
and consequence and presence
people begin to attest to it they lie to
a certain extent about the meaning of
your life because the lies about you
are as true as the true things about you
tend to be
and somewhere in there you begin to gain
some kind of status in people's memories
and they begin to refer to you in
various ways
and that's how you come to mean
something you see so
the meaning of your life is not your
intention the meaning of your life
is granted to you by others
that's how you begin to make peace with
it
and you practice doing that by
participating
in the cobbling together of the meaning
of other people's lives
in the wake of their dying music
which is to say then that everyone's
death before your own
is your chance to get it right to get a
phd in the way it really is
and the degree to which you stay away
from the dying of other people for all
kinds of crazy reasons
is the degree to which you will come to
your own death
as an amateur and as a rookie and as a
beginner
and it's not a good time you know to
have that status
case in point a woman comes up to me
at the end of some talk i did years ago
and she's in her mid-50s probably she
says well that's really good you know
and everything but it's not that useful
to me
i said she said yeah really because
here's why
nobody close to me has died
and i did i thought to myself it's very
clear she doesn't realize that she's
confessing
to me right now and what she's
confessing is this and it's sad
she's saying she's lived her life in
such a way
as to have kept people at a distance of
course people have been dying around her
but she's moderated the consequence by
keeping her distance from them
so alas it's true nobody close to her
has died can you imagine what her dying
would be like
so two competing questions are coming
one is you know the inquiry about
why we are not collectively practicing
this skill
and the other one is how do we get to
practice this skill but then it's kind
of being
like a more immediate question is coming
to mind um about the present moment
and your take on it this whole pandemic
and the crisis that we're in
well i'll come to the thing you didn't
quite ask first
and and then
[Music]
if you can hear me stephen your uh video
has just frozen
yeah there we go is that good again yeah
it's good
okay uh lord oh
what i was saying in is this
language is the way by which we approach
the world
it's the way by which the world becomes
available accessible
present consequential to us
so the first order of business always
when you're trying to figure out how to
is you attend to the language that
you're bringing to bear
upon the thing you've identified as a
problem you see
the language will never let you down
if you're faithful to it but you know
it's it's
it sounds strange to tell a grown-up
that you have to learn the language
because most people are offended by that
they think they know it quite well
but i can tell you my stock and trade is
language that's all i really have
that's the only skillfulness i seem to
be lucky enough to have
and i'm thinking about it all the time
but
more important than that i'm practicing
it all the time
i'm not just talking i'm practicing
wonder by exercising
the language out at it's the limit of
what i'm accustomed to
see so i'm not saying to you something
i've said a thousand times before
in other kinds of interviews i'm not i'm
i'm trying to approach the very thing
that you're asking me about with
in the very circumstance we find
ourselves in
every time you know i'm asked to do so
so i i take that to be a moral
obligation not a circus trick
see so the act of wondering
is the linguistic function first and
foremost
here's what i mean by that i'll give you
five seconds
this is a bit of a joke but just see if
you can play along with it
see it think of a thought you've never
thought before
go okay
it's it's really hard
why because
because it can't come to you as a
spontaneously
generated thing it comes to you
mediated to you by language that you are
familiar with
right but you might have to rearrange
the language
and the new arrangement that you've been
able to achieve
somehow gives you another track to begin
to wonder and to pursue
but it's the rearrangement of the
language that comes first
so what comes first developmentally for
us
is it seeing or is it saying
virtually everyone would say seeing
comes first and eventually the language
catches up
but here's the thing you have a very
difficult time remembering
stuff from your very early life why do
you suppose that is
because they know that developmentally
there's a relationship between
speech acquisition and memory retention
wow that's there's some real magic there
you realize that it's your language
that's giving you your capacity to
remember things so you speak your way
towards the thing that you're trying to
recall
you've done it a million times you know
you're trying to say something
i forget how it went and then you
somehow you find a bit of a thread you
say three words and
bang the whole association is there
again
and you have recall right
and of course recall is a verbal
activity
it means to summon or to plead for the
presence of
again that's what recall means we use
that as a synonym for memory
okay with that in mind i would
then say what you hear me trying to do
is practice something that i it's trick
i learned from meditation people i
should say
i don't know anything about meditation
i've never done it
i probably secretly envy the people who
do do it
but i don't envy them enough to learn
how to do it myself
so there you go but one of the things
that they found a way to do
is to take something they were going to
be doing anyway
and elevate it to a devotional degree
and the something in question was
breathing
it's an amazing observation they take
the most ordinary and mundane of
of detail and turn it into an object
object of real contemplation
in the act of doing it so they bring
their breath you understand what i'm
saying to
to the level of real alertness and they
employ the breath
to wonder and to try to
achieve a degree of presentness and all
that kind of thing
i do that with speaking i've come to
realize this about myself
i'm i'm a kind of late blooming
meditation practitioner when it comes to
language yeah right
that's what you hear me doing now so the
irony is
50 minutes into an interview somebody
will say to me
so so how do we come to a different
understanding about
well let's say dying and i say dude i've
just been talking about that for
fifth minute and now you're asking me
for some kind of magic answer
right or magic bullet you see yeah okay
so with that in mind let me see if i can
stumble
towards what's quote happening now
you know i'm looking out the window at
the
melt water that's increasing
by a third again the river right in
front of my farm here
it looks the same as yesterday but
there's a little more water than it was
in the farm in the field behind me
the first twins were born sheep i should
say
and this is the beginning of new life
here on the farm
and it's a spectacularly beautiful day
which is very good for my solar panels
and uh as soon as we're finished i have
to go prepare
a wood pile for transfer to dry out for
next year just in case things get really
hairy
okay so what am i saying i'm saying
at many many levels things are unfolding
exactly as they do at the beginning of
april in the northern hemisphere
that's not an insignificant thing to
think
at a time like this okay
i'm not pretending that almost
everything's the same
but the meaning of everything is seems
to be scattered
a lot of things a lot of the natural
order is proceeding more or less
as it must because it's calendrically
faithful
in a way that we don't know how to be
okay so the epidemiologists quote know
that there was a province if that's what
they call them in china
there's a province and inside the
province in china there was a city
and inside that city there was a market
and inside that market there was an area
they called a wet market and inside that
zone
they had been in cages domestic animals
and wild animals given their insane and
indefensible penchant
for the exotic to put in their mouths to
augment their
for virility or fertility whatever the
hell it is
and if that's as far as you go with
understanding what's happening
you're kind of in the in the realm of
alleged
principal causes but you've missed
something fundamental
and it's the it's that little
architecture of the wild
being brought into obscene proximity to
the domesticated
and we know that the virus leapt across
that chasm
from the wild animal to the domestic
animal and subsequently to the person
who handled the animal to sell or to
butcher and to sell
and subsequently to those who ate it
that's what that's what happened
okay so so the the lesson to be learned
and the thing to be understood is
this is a direct consequence of humans
going
where they shouldn't be going and the
should
comes from this it doesn't come from
some moral order
it comes from an understanding that the
wild can only be wild to the extent that
we stay
out of it we have the consequence
particularly in our numbers
and particularly with our technologies
to to obviate the wild
every time we go the wild retreats
you see that's what it does and the
people in their
wild ayahuasca you know fantasies
imagine
that they're one with the wild and all
this crazy shit
if you investigate you know what happens
to these people on these magical mystery
rides
one of the things that becomes clear is
the wild is absolutely overwhelming to
them
so there's a lesson to be learned there
we're not going back
to the wild we've never been there it's
not our home
there's clearly too many of us and we're
going to all kinds of places we don't
belong and our lack of belonging has now
come
scorpions tale-wise up from behind us
and is killing us in two or three days
after we're exposed
at least if you're my age or we have
predisposing circumstances and so on
so this is a kind of moral play that's
unfolding before us
yeah right that's what it is we're we're
paying the price of exercising a
dominion
the responsibility for which we cannot
live
we have no capacity to live there's a
very clear parallel for me
to the death trait when i was working in
the death trade
we had a kind of technology and
medicinal arsenal
that if you really knew what they could
do to you
you'd be un unnerved and overwhelmed by
it to be honest with you
we can overcome overwhelm and overturn
almost virtually every bodily function
we can do it mechanically or we can do
it drug induced wise
my point in telling you this is that
we have a kind of uh technological
innovation that is forever
leaping ahead of itself right it's
outgrowing itself
so exponentially that nobody certainly
not the physicians
can keep track of it in the old days
this is what they used to resort to they
had medical
technological innovation yes but they
had a kind of practice
wisdom that would guide the use of the
technology
and temper the consequences and the
resorting to
the innovation now
being tempered and being being held back
by practice wisdom that's become a
suckers game
that's for old people and people your
age and younger than you
look upon something like that as an
unnecessary
limit on what could be virtually
limitless possibilities and the
giddiness that ensues from that
when everything is bright and sunny the
giddiness from that
is very welcome this is no different
what you're looking at now is all the
consequences of innovation minus the
regulating function
of practice wisdom which is derived from
what
from previous practice and so on it's
accumulative you see
and the problem now is anybody my age
is basically thrown on the trash heap of
insignificance by people in their 20s
why because the the gadgetry
that's enabling you and i to speak right
now is something that's designed for
people with little fingers
you see i'm saying for 12 year olds or
10 year olds
everybody knows that's what that's who
they're identifying and that's who
they're
they're focusing they're selling to not
to somebody like me
they couldn't care less whether i agree
with the disagree they think it's the
demon
demons playground or any devil's
playground i should say i guess
and all of that is just to say
that when you decide to go it alone
generationally
and you decide experience is another
kind of limit that you don't need to
agree to or to submit yourself to
be not surprised that there are
consequences that you did not intend
and this is not sin you see i'm not this
is not in a sense
a kind of moral failing of humans this
is something
that comes from our lack of practice of
any kind of initiatory
um you know culture
strategy that's designed to limit and
then finally to end
childhood right a childhood extends into
the people's 30s and 40s now
with alarming frequency right and uh
you know the notion of of wanting to be
personally safe
i mean i wrote a book and there's a
chapter in there called uh
oh my god i'm blanking on the name of
the chapter but the the notion is
that um that there there's no such thing
as safety and that's what grown-ups know
and the clamoring after personal safety
or a safe space all that kind of stuff
is a sign that you don't really need
you don't really want to befriend the
world in its own term
what you want the world to do is to
submit to your sense of insecurity
right that's what i'm saying so all of
that
i know i'm going on and off for a long
time but that last thing
what do you make of what's going on well
yeah what i'm looking at
is the unclaimed bastard children of our
excesses
that's what this is and you know all i
can say
as a kind of plea is this
i'm old enough to remember what the
american government in its lunacy
recommended to its populace in the
aftermath of their famous 9 11 national
holiday
they told everybody to go out shop
because that's the best way to fight
al-qaeda
they literally said that shit okay it's
very clear in my
my memory because the utter
the kind of larcenous
ludicrousness of it was so overwhelming
it kind of
beggared your imagination for a time i
promise you this
what they're going to mount on the back
end of this thing will make
that look like child's play you know
so i would you know conclude this part
of things by saying to you
i think that what's happened is the
visitation of a god
okay not in the form of punishment i
don't think punishment is in
the god's repertoire that's a human
construct
but the gods are very much about
consequence
they visit consequence because they're
faithful practitioners of the natural
order of things and that's the scenario
i was telling you about
in the market that's exactly what that
is
so this is a god in the same way the
death is a god
and what it's giving us a chance to do
is something we never would have done
voluntarily
and what's that to stop
that's what and they say i don't know
this for a fact but they say the water
is running clear
in the lagoons in venice for the first
time in anybody's memory
and you could point to a thousand maybe
ten thousand examples that are similar
across the world a direct consequence
of our habits being broken is that the
world is breathing
easier and it's tragic that it comes to
life
it's absolutely tragic
but we can either you know i i have a
i have a band as you may know and i have
a we've been doing a show off and on
for five years and we had 70 city four
continent tour
arranged uh to start this month in about
three weeks from now on
things are going the way they're going
but in their
the idea that i wondered about many
times
was not so much what's to become of us
or but what has become of us and
one of the points i made is you know
there's an oracle
by the highway as you enter or leave a
city
you you can if you look for it you'll
see it it's an oracle
it's a masquerading as a highway sign
what does it say
it says be prepared to stop
that's an oracle you see and
look we've already clicked past being
prepared to stop
and now be prepared to be stopped
has become the new world order
and we have been stopped
and i think the crime
the indefensible crime will be
to resume right standard broadcast
practice right that'll be
that'll be so unspeakably obscene
and it'll look so non-eventful to do so
in actual fact we have no obligation to
resume the life that we had
two or three weeks ago
sorry you're about to say something um
that we're at the hour mark too so uh
maybe i'll say this and we can we can
land
the plane with it um yeah you said so
much things then there's like
20 different conversational threats here
popping up uh about elderhood narcissism
um present moment but but something
that was quite salient for me and
[Music]
i don't know if it was what you were
saying or how you were saying it but
just really snapped me into a different
state
um and this idea of the way i hold like
truth versus truthfulness
um like truth is like use the
philosophical term the correspondence
theory of truth
if your model of reality maps over to
reality and it's accurate then you got
the truth
and you can replicate it scientifically
and then blah blah people memorize it in
institutions and repeat it
that's different than and truthfulness
is that's what i'm holding what you're
doing
where you're just kind of like
constantly mapping your words to the
present moment your experience your
emotions your thoughts the states
and then you're in flow um with reality
with god
uh and you have a relationship with
daemon when you do that
accurately and assuming that's true
and if people become unfaithful to
to being truthful that truthfulness then
they become
deceased you know then the disease the
disease spreads
um and so that this kind of connection
just hit me when you kind of
talked about the way you're truthful
with the present state of this pandemic
and then the relationship between the
two and it kind of like i
you know i knew this propositionally and
i try to practice my truthfulness as
best i can
but it seems um the ethical obligation
for me to do so
and model it and help encourage other
people to do it just got heightened
in that moment yeah it was amen
you know the the the tragic realization
that
we are obliged to come to as adults in a
time like
not such as this in this time
is that quote first of all everybody's
not doing their best let's just get it
straight okay
if everybody was doing their best shit
wouldn't be what it is
okay that's the first thing second of
all left to our devices
at least the dominant culture north
american characters that i've grown up
with and come to know
myself included left our own devices
our hearts become a comfort seeking
missile man
that's the that's the crude
savage sorrow of our time is it
left to ourselves we will seek the path
of least resistance
we will seek short-term you know
soothing and all of that stuff
you know a safe place to play um
everybody wants what we want you know
it's just all the all the sad and
trite quote truisms that pass for things
that have actually been observed
they're not observed you're advocating
for them because you can't
find them where's my safe place
there's no such thing and and these days
certainly illustrate this right these
people in uh
oh people in the old folks home all
folks homes are an obscenity i mean
let's just get it straight
and all of a sudden they're all dying in
their legions in an old folks home
yeah because you're not supposed to have
a slender portion of the population
overly represented in a given place
you're not supposed to have too many
kids in one place
like these these trance festivals and
shit where you don't have the presence
of uh of gravity bringing
older people by which younger people can
look at their swooning
and ask themselves is this really a deep
participation in life
you can't ask that if everybody's
swooning together at the same time
see you got too many old people in one
place what do you got and
on and on it goes you see so this wicked
segregation
means nobody no good and this is what
cults look like cults by definition tend
to be one generation wide
right right okay so we have a little
farm here
and we got let me see
well we got three generations living on
the farm all at the same time
it's not an experiment it's as old as
the hills
right and we're just lucky enough that
people are
deciding to live this way in close
proximity to each other
stumbling about in the dark trying to
figure it out
that's all it is and you know we're
lucky enough to have it
and to be reminded of these things
constantly by virtue
simply of the presence of somebody who's
not your generation
i'm not placing all of the onus for
being wise upon older people by saying
this i'm not
i'm saying it's it's it's the miracle
alchemy
of the juxtaposition of the generations
that produce the capacity to see things
for what they are
the extent to which you keep them apart
is the extent to which we become
inaccessible to each other and finally
the world itself
becomes a a kind of savage
uh withholding kind of unkindness
to us as if because the the world is not
orchestrated to
satisfy us then it's by definition
hostile
right so if you watch other generations
of people
engaging with this thing just as you
reported as a consequence of the way i
was saying a certain something
things can change man right
and well i mean there's no way to sum
any of this stuff up and i know we're at
the end of our time
so i'm not going to try to sum it up but
i'll just say
what that the time comes
that some people remember this time
as as a time when things fundamentally
did change i know that's the language
that's being used right now
but the change has not occurred change
has been forced upon us at the moment
that's not a change the change will be
there
when the force is removed and the
willingness to live differently
remains
and what i'm leaving with um
is sort of like the question how to find
the elders well i found one right now
on the zoom chat um and then you know
jordan peterson comes to mind how
everyone just gravitated to him as the
father figure of the
internet type thing uh
yeah yeah fellow trontonian um
he was my therapist actually for two
years before he became
super famous so it was interesting just
to see his rise and everyone just kind
of like
attracted to him um and just the other
thing i'm leaving with is that
returning back to that truthfulness is
um it's sort of like
it's hard being truthful in a lot of
circumstances because there's that
tension
and it's like you're constantly
sacrificing when you're when you're
being truthful you're
constantly sacrificing something to
comfort your ego whatever
and it's like the thought that just came
up is like if you can do that
consistently reliably
then it's like there's a readiness there
for for death
there's an ability i'm not sure the word
ready is the most useful word to use
you know it's still shocking look man
this the shit is still crazy making
it is right but what what i'm advocating
is the idea
that if you attend enough deaths before
your own
then there's something about dying it's
not that it's familiar
it's that it's it's not lethal
[Music]
it's not any more lethal than the day
that you're born i mean it's a rough
ride
right okay and it's a rough ride to die
whether it's fast or slow it's a rough
ride
and you're going to do it more or less
alone and the good news is
that there is a kind of way
that's been established by the people
who died before you
and the deaths prior to your own
establish your ancestry
and the indigenous part of you is
vaguely hip to the understanding
that you're wherever you're headed it's
where everybody who died before you is
headed
you don't really have to initiate
anything
your skillfulness comes from knowing
that you're not the first one
isn't that a remarkable kind of skill to
get in line for shit sakes
right right it is yeah cool
so so i'm gonna uh stop the record um
but thank you so much for coming on the
the podcast today
uh is there anything that you'd like to
leave the people listening
right now with where they can find you
maybe or sure
um i mentioned that i you know i had a
band and we had a tour all lined up and
all of that sort of thing well we're
still coming
we're still we're still going to play i
mean we're making a record right now
it's going to be released probably in
about a month and a half and the event
is called knights of grief and mystery
we don't have a name for the band we
have a name for the event
nights of grief and mystery and if there
is ever a time
built and made for a night of
grief and mystery devoted to that as a
practice
you see as a practice not an experience
that grief and mystery
are practices that's what we do we're
going to get on the road as soon as we
can
as soon as it's in some fashion or other
sustainable and of course all the
all the economics have changed
witheringly and god
only knows how we're going to be able to
do it and all the rest
but orphan wisdom.com is where all the
information is and
and uh we're coming to europe i believe
in
june if it's you know it's gonna be
tight obviously
but that's our intent we got gigs all
the way out to
israel and all the way up to sweden
and uh we'll see how it goes
indefinitely
in the fall in north america and
australia in november and december
and uh i have a school and uh
whatever you heard comes from doing all
these things
you know and i'm very lucky that people
have decided to
come to watch a rock and roll band
headed by a 65 year old guy who's never
done it
it's a gig yeah
that's awesome okay i'll include all
that on the show notes as well for those
who are listening
okay thank you